A Finding Aid to the Percy Leason Papers, circa 1929-2011, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Percy Leason papers
circa 1929-2011
Archives of American Art
Leason, Percy, 1889-1959
AAA.leasperc
Archival Resource Key
1.3 Linear feet
0.402 Gigabytes
The papers of painter, illustrator, and educator Percy Leason measure 1.3 linear feet and 0.402 GB and date from circa 1929 to 2011. The collection documents his career through biographical material, correspondence, diaries, writings and notes, printed and digital material, photographic material, and a scrapbook.
Biographical / Historical
Percy Leason (1889-1959) was a painter, illustrator, writer, and educator from Kaniva, Victoria in Australia. Leason took an interest in art at an early age winning first prize in painting at the 1904 State Fair. He later attended art school in the town of Nhill, and in 1906, he went to Melbourne to be an apprentice at Sands and McDougall Lithographers. Soon after starting his apprenticeship, Leason moved to the art department where he began drawing illustrations for products and advertisements. In the evenings, he attended the Melbourne Gallery School where he studied art under Bernard Hall and Frederick McCubbin. While in Melbourne, Leason associated himself with the Victorian Artist Society and lived a bohemian lifestyle. He began creating illustrations for books in 1914 and went on to do illustrations for the Sydney Bulletin, Melbourne Punch, Tabletalk Magazine, and the Melbourne Herald where he developed the Wiregrass cartoon series. In 1924, Leason and Max Meldrum, who Leason had met a few years before, discussed tonal realism, a systematic style of painting that uses light and shade to produce a misty quality. Leason's devotion to tonal realism along with his participation in Victorian Artist Society exhibitions helped advance his career. In 1934 Melbourne University commissioned him to do a series on Australian aborigines. He became interested in cave art and archeology during this time. In Cambridge, England in 1937 he presented his theory that cave artists sketched using dead animals as models.
Due to the impending World War, art scene rivalries, and the lack of commercial art employment prospects, Leason immigrated to New York in 1938 in search of more opportunities in the United States. Before emigrating to the U.S., he completed a portrait of Basil Burdett which now hangs in the Queensland Art Gallery in Brisbane, Australia. His career in New York included work for New York Daily News, Blue Book Magazine, the Saturday Evening Post, Street and Smith, and book illustrations for The Wizard of Oz by Frank Baum (Whitman Publishing Company) in 1939. In New York, Leason continued his opposition to modernist and expressionist art by aligning himself with the Salmagundi Club, Allied Artists, and the American Artist Professional League, all of which supported tonal realism. In association with Portraits Incorporated in New York, he painted the portraits of TV personality Arlene Francis, Michael Engel of Grumbacker art supplies, and Missouri congressman Dewey Short whose portrait is housed in the House of Representative's collection in Washington D.C.
By the late 1950's, Leason had difficulties within the art world because the trends in art no longer held a place for his tonal realism. He died in 1959 on Staten Island in New York. As a tribute to Leason after his death, the Staten Island Institute and the Salmagundi Club held retrospective exhibitions of his work.
Scope and Contents
The papers of painter, illustrator, and educator Percy Leason measure 1.3 linear feet and 0.402 GB and date from circa 1929 to 2011. The collection documents his career through biographical material, correspondence, diaries, writings and notes, printed and digital material, photographic material, and a scrapbook.
Biographical materials include financial records, biographical statements about the artist, certificates, and a few sketches. Correspondence contains letters and writings of Max Leason, Percy Leason's son, correspondence to and from Percy Leason, letters from congressmen, and letters regarding Leason's work displayed at the State Library of Victoria in Australia. Four diaries document Leason's life over 20 years. A series of published and unpublished writings and notes includes two digital books of Leason's writings. Printed material contains new clippings, gallery flyers, a framed statement about art, and the book The Science of Appearances by Max Meldrum with typed pages written by Leason inserted into the book. Photographic materials include slides and digital photographs of Leason's artwork, personal photographs, and photographs of the State Library of Victoria. One scrapbook contains mostly news clippings and other printed material.
Scattered throughout the collection are annotations made by Max Leason which are usually signed "Max" with the date of annotation.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated in 1969-1979 and 2014 by Max A. Leason, Percy Leason's son.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 7 series.
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1939-1957, 2006 (5 folders; Box 1, 2)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1946-1973 (4 folders, Box 1)
Series 3: Diaries, 1938-1959 (0.3 linear ft.; Box 1)
Series 4: Writings and Notes, 1939-2011 (6 folders, Box 1, 0.155 GB; ER01-ER02)
Series 5: Printed Material, circa 1946-1973 (4 folders; Box 1)
Series 6: Photographic Materials, circa 1969-1972 (0.2 linear ft.; Box 1, 2, 0.247 GB; ER03)
Series 7: Scrapbook, 1938-1972 (0.1 linear ft.; Box 2)
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reels 74, 999-1000, 1050 and 3090 at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Photographs; Sketches; Painters -- New York (State) -- Staten Island; Illustrators -- New York (State) -- Staten Island; Scrapbooks; Diaries; Leason, Max; Meldrum, Max, 1875-1955; State Library of Victoria
- Biographical Material, 1939-1957; 2006; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 5 Folders Box 1, 2
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical material includes an account book, account ledger, biographical statement written by Max Leason, Percy Leason's son, for AskArt.com, and certificates awarded by the Salmagundi Club, the Staten Island Institute of Arts and Sciences, and the Audubon Artists. Also included are six small sketches of figures in historical costume and one sketch of a boat.
  - Account Book, 1943-1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Account Ledger, 1939-1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical Statements, 2006; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sketches, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Certificates, 1947-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1946-1973; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 4 Folders Box 1
  Correspondence includes the letters and writings of Max Leason regarding Percy Leason's artwork, membership status, and manuscripts sent to and from printers, museums, and art related organizations. Also within Max Leason's correspondence is a curriculum vitae for Percy Leason. The correspondence of Percy Leason documents his efforts to have his manuscripts published and contains letters expressing his opinions on art. Also found in correspondence are two letters from the U.S. House of Representatives, sent after Leason's death, requesting portraits of John McCormack, Overton Brooks, and James E. Van Zandt. Correspondence with the State Library of Victoria regarding an inventory of Leason's work that was deposited at the library is also included in this series.
  - Correspondence and Writings of Max Leason Regarding Percy Leason, 1968-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence Sent and Received by Percy Leason, 1946-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters from U.S. Congressmen, 1959; 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The State Library of Victoria, circa 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Diaries, 1938-1959; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  This series includes four diaries that span over 20 years. The diaries document Leason's daily activities and thoughts. This series may include letters and news clippings that are either loose or pasted into the diaries.
  - Diary, 1938-1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Diary, circa 1948-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Diary, 1950; 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Diary, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Writings and Notes, 1939-2011; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 6 Folders Box 1; 0.155 Gigabytes ER01-ER02
  Found within this series are Leason's notes on A Brief History of Painting, Paleolithic Art, and The Science of Appearances. Also included are published works by Leason in the Proceedings of the Staten Island Institute of Arts and Sciences, The Artist, and Australia. Also included are digital versions of "Artist of Modern Times: the Biography of Percy Leason" by Max Leason and "Experience in Painting: An Analysis of the Visual Impression as Applied to Painting" by Percy Leason, edited by Max Leason.
  - "Artist of Modern Times: The Biography of Percy Leason", by Max Leason, Digital Document, 2011; Archival Resource Key; 0.036 Gigabytes One computer file (Folder ER01)
  - "Experience in Painting: An Analysis of the Visual Impression as Applied to Painting" by Percy Leason, edited by Max Leason, Digital Document, 2010; Archival Resource Key; 0.119 Gigabytes One computer file (Folder ER02)
  - Notes on "A Brief History of Painting", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Notes on Paleolithic Art, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Notes on "The Science of Appearances", circa 1950's; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Published Work, 1939-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Printed Material, 1973; circa 1946-1973; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 4 Folders Box 1
  Printed material consists of news clippings about Max Meldrum, flyers from the Adams, Davidson Galleries, a framed statement about art, and a reporduction of the Dewey Short portrait by Leason with a printed program from the portrait's unveiling. The book by Max Meldrum, The Science of Appearances, has typed writings by Leason inserted into the book where Leason thought appropriate.
  - Adams, Davidson Galleries, Inc., 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - News Clippings About Max Meldrum, circa 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Framed Statement About Art, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Reproduction of Dewey Short Portrait, 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - The Science of Apearances by Max Meldrum, 1950-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Photographic Materials, circa 1929-1970s; 2010; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1, 2; 0.247 Gigabytes ER03
  Photographic materials contains photographs and digital photographs and slides of Leason's artwork, and some personal photographs showing candid photographs of Leason, a photo of Arlene Francis with her portrait, and Leason at work. Some of the digital images may be duplicates of the slides and photographs.
  - Paintings, Digital Photographs, 2010; Archival Resource Key; 0.247 Gigabytes 348 computer files (Folder ER03)
  - Photographs of Artwork, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Photographs of Artwork, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Photographs, Personal, circa 1929-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Slides of Artwork, circa 1950s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Slides of Artwork, circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - The State Library of Victoria, circa 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Scrapbook, 1938-1972; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 2
  The scrapbook contains mainly news clippings and other printed material documenting Leason's career in Australia and New York. A few pieces of correspondence and notes are also included.
  - Scrapbook, 1938-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2)